Guide to the George Louis Kline Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Louis Kline papers
1965-2000
GEN MSS 650
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5
(5 boxes)
The collection documents George L. Kline's work as a translator for Joseph Brodsky and related activities, including the translation of other Russian prose and poetry and scholarship on Russian literature. Included are correspondence, drafts of Brodsky's poems and Kline's English translations, sound recordings of Brodsky, and photographs of Brodsky and others. Other than Brodsky, correspondents include W. H. Auden, Nina Berberova, Leonid Chertkov, Anthony Hecht, Lev Losev, Faith Wizgell and Igor Efimov. Manuscripts include signed typescripts of several of Brodsky's poems and typescript poems of Evgenii Rein inscribed to Joseph Brodsky. Among the sound recordings is a recording of Brodsky reciting his poems in 1968 in his Leningrad apartment, recorded by George Kline.
Kline, George L. (George Louis), 1921-2014
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George L. Kline, 2008.
Appraisal
The George Louis Kline Papers were acquired to complement the Joseph Brodsky Papers. The Beinecke Library acquired papers that document Kline's translations of Brodsky's poetry and of other Russian prose and poetry. Papers that document Kline's lengthy career as a professor at Bryn Mawr College and his scholarship in other domains were not acquired.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Access to original audiovisual recordings is restricted. Researchers should consult the Beinecke Library Access Services department for policies and procedures for the creation of reference copies, if none exist.
George Louis Kline (b. 1921)
George L. Kline, professor emeritus at Bryn Mawr College, is a scholar of philosophy and literature and translates Russian prose and poetry. His translations include the poetry of Joseph Brodsky, Marina Tsvetaeva and Anna Akhmatova.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents George L. Kline's work as a translator for Joseph Brodsky and related activities, including the translation of other Russian prose and poetry and scholarship on Russian literature. Included are correspondence, drafts of Brodsky's poems and Kline's English translations, sound recordings of Brodsky, and photographs of Brodsky and others. Other than Brodsky, correspondents include W. H. Auden, Nina Berberova, Leonid Chertkov, Anthony Hecht, Lev Losev, Faith Wigzell and Igor Efimov. Manuscripts include signed typescripts of several of Brodsky's poems and typescript poems of Evgenii Rein inscribed to Joseph Brodsky. Among the sound recordings is a recording of Brodsky reciting his poems in 1968 in his Leningrad apartment, recorded by George Kline.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1972-2000. II. Writings, circa 1965-2000. III. Other Papers, circa 1978-1996.
Authors, Russian; Poetry -- Translations into English; Poetry -- 20th Century; Poets, Russian -- 20th Century; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Russian poetry -- 20th Century; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Photographs; Sound recordings; Translators; Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973; Berberova, N. (Nina), 1901-1993; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996; Chertkov, Leonid, 1933-2000; Efimov, Igorʹ Markovich; Hecht, Anthony, 1923-2004; Kline, George L. (George Louis), 1921-2014; Losev, Lev, 1937-2009; Reĭn, Evgeniĭ; Wigzell, Faith
- Correspondence, 1972-2000; Series I; 1.2
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Correspondence with Joseph Brodsky, Correspondence about Joseph Brodsky, and Other Correspondence.
  - Correspondence with Joseph Brodsky
    - Incoming letters and copies of outgoing letters, 1972-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence about Joseph Brodsky
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. One folder of correspondence with publishers is filed at the end of the alphabetic listing.
    - "A" general (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Auden, W.H. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Anscheutz, Carol (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "B" general (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "C" general (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chalsma, Bill (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "D" general (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dunham, Vera (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "E" general (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - English, Maurice (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "F" general (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Farrar, Straus & Giroux (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "G" general (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "H" general (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Haight, Amanda (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Haven, Cynthia (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "I" general (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "J" general (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "K" general (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Kocher, Karel (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "L" general (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "M" general (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "N" general (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "P" general (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "R" general (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "S" general (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Schlitz, Veronique (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Shtern, Ludmila (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Stangos, Nikos (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Steckler, Irene (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Struve, Gleb (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "T" general (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Triquarterly (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "U-V" general (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Viereck, Peter (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "W" general (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Wigzell, Faith (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Wolfe, Bertram and Ella (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - "Y-Z" general (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Zenkovsky, Betty Jean (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence with publishers (Box 1, Folder 44-46)
    - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Other Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - "A-G" general (Box 1, Folder 48-54)
    - Harper & Row (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - "I-L" general (Box 1, Folder 56-58)
    - Losev, Lev (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - "M-N" general (Box 1, Folder 60-61)
    - Naiman, Anatoly (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "O-V" general (Box 2, Folder 63-68)
    - Vashestov, Andrei (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Venclova, Tomas (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Volkogonova, Ol'ga (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - "Y-Z" general (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Zenkovsky, Betty Jean (Box 2, Folder 73)
- Writings, circa 1965-2000; Series II; 2.8
  Scope and Contents
  Includes typescripts (originals and photocopies) of Joseph Brodsky's poetry in Russian, many annotated by Kline, drafts of Kline's translations, some corrected by Kline and/or Brodsky, and a holograph manuscript of an occasional poem Brodsky wrote for Kline ("Fast-shrift (sic) for George L. Kline"). Also present is a proof of Ostanovka v Pustyne, heavily corrected by Brodsky. Among George Kline's writings and translations are drafts of English translations of poetry by Anna Akhmatova, Boris Pasternak, and Marina Tsvetaeva, among others. Also present are two folders of clean copies of Kline's published writings, 1949-1970.
  Organized into three subseries: Joseph Brodsky Writings, George L. Kline Writings, and Other Writings.
  - Joseph Brodsky Writings
    Not arranged in any particular order.
    - "Fast-shrift for George L. Kline," holograph, signed (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - "Didi i Enei," holograph, signed (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - "We do believe in ...," holograph (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "Strofy," typescript, inscribed to Kline (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Translations of John Donne (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Ostanovka v Pustyne, printed version, annotated by Kline (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Various poems, typescripts, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Prose writings, typescripts, photocopies and printed versions (Box 2, Folder 81-84)
  - George L. Kline Writings and Translations
    Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    Files contain drafts of translations, essays, lectures and correspondence related to Kline's translations of Russian poetry and literary analyses.
    - Akhmatova, Anna (Box 2, Folder 85-93)
    - Bely, Andrei (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Brodsky, Joseph
      - Translations, drafts and notes (Box 2, Folder 95-100)
      - "JB for Kontinent (English edition)" (Box 2, Folder 101)
      - "Eclogue 5" (Box 2, Folder 102)
      - "20 Sonnets" (Box 2, Folder 103)
      - "Biblical ..." (Box 3, Folder 104)
      - "Razvivaia Platona" (Box 3, Folder 105)
      - "Living Mirror" (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - "Nazidanie" (Box 3, Folder 107)
      - "Razgovor s nebozhitelem" (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - "The butterfly" (Box 3, Folder 109)
      - "Cape Cod Lullaby" (Box 3, Folder 110)
      - "Translations since Selected Poems " (Box 3, Folder 111)
      - "For QSP" (Box 3, Folder 112)
      - "Vtoroe Rozhdestvo" (Box 3, Folder 113)
      - "Newest Poems" (Box 3, Folder 114)
      - "Six New Poems," annotated by Brodsky (Box 3, Folder 115)
      - Copies of typescripts of Russian-language versions of Brodsky's poetry (Box 3, Folder 116-121)
      - Kline interviews of Brodsky (Box 3, Folder 122-124)
      - Kline essays and other writings on Brodsky (Box 3, Folder 125-132)
      - "Istoriia dvukh knig" (Box 3, Folder 133-135)
      - "Variations on the theme of exile" (Box 3, Folder 136)
      - "Muhlenberg talk" (Box 3, Folder 137-139)
      - Selected Poems, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 140-145)
      - "Translating Brodsky (Box 3, Folder 146)
      - "Poeziia Brodskogo" (Box 3, Folder 147)
      - New and Selected Poems ("Second edition") (Box 3, Folder 148)
      - "Brodsky/Rein/Kushner BMC Talk", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 149)
      - "A Part of Speech" (Box 3, Folder 150)
      - "Revising Brodsky" (Box 3, Folder 151)
      - "Bibliography" (Box 3, Folder 152)
      - "Chronology" (Box 3, Folder 153-154)
      - Unidentified notes (Box 3, Folder 155-157)
      - "Brodsky Conference", 1991 (Box 4, Folder 158)
      - "Presepio" (Box 4, Folder 159-160)
    - Kushner, Aleksandr (Box 4, Folder 161-162)
    - Okhapkin, O. (Box 4, Folder 163)
    - Pasternak, Boris (Box 4, Folder 164-172)
    - Rein, Evgenii, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 173-175)
    - Skovoroda, Hryhorii (Box 4, Folder 176)
    - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr (Box 4, Folder 177)
    - Tolstoy, Lev (Box 4, Folder 178-179)
    - Tsvetaeva, Marina (Box 4, Folder 180-183)
    - Essays on translating Russian poetry (Box 4, Folder 184-186)
    - "Published articles 1949-1963" (Box 4, Folder 187)
    - "Published articles 1964-1970" (Box 4, Folder 188)
    - Abstracts of essays on philosophy (Box 4, Folder 189)
  - Other Writings
    - Translations of Brodsky by others (Box 4, Folder 190-193)
    - W.H. Auden's foreword to Brodsky's Selected Poems (Box 4, Folder 194-198)
    - "Russian poetry manuscripts" (Box 4, Folder 199)
      Typescripts of poems by Evgenii Rein, Vladimir Ufliand, Leonid Chertkov, Dmitri Bobyshev and ____ Krasovedskii.
- Other Papers, circa 1978-1996; Series III; 1
  - Material for Brodsky poetry readings (Box 5, Folder 200-202)
  - Material from Brodsky's memorial, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 203)
  - Reviews of Brodsky and of Kline's translations (Box 5, Folder 204-205)
  - Printed articles about Brodsky (Box 5, Folder 206)
  - Photographs of Joseph Brodsky and George Kline (Box 5, Folder 207-213)
  - Clippings related to Brodsky (Box 5, Folder 214-215)
  - Sound recordings (Box 5, Folder 216-225)
    Twelve audiocassettes, including a 1968 recording of Brodsky reciting his poetry in his Leningrad apartment.